Our convention program contains
今見たドラマを含め
この地区大会のプログラムには
over 100 audio and video productions,
100を超えるビデオやオーディオの
コンテンツが含まれています
including the one we just enjoyed.
These videos are made
at various locations around the world.
ビデオは世界中のいろいろな
場所で制作されています
We have the privilege of supporting this
私たちはそうした王国の活動を
金銭面で支えられます
and other aspects of the Kingdom work.
For your convenience,
donations can be made online
オンラインで寄付を行うことができます
donate.jw.orgを
ご覧ください
at donate.jw.org.
ドラマで見たように
As we saw,
ダニエルは試練に遭っても
老齢になっても 強い信仰を保ちました
the prophet Daniel maintained his faith
despite tests and infirmities.
How can we do the same?
私たちもそうできるでしょうか
What strength can we gain
from the prophetic visions given to Daniel?
ダニエルが見た幻から
どのように力が得られますか
Please pay close attention
統治体のスティーブン・レット兄弟の
話に注目しましょう
to Brother Stephen Lett of the Governing Body
結びの話の中で
疑問に答えてくださいます
as he answers those questions
in the final talk
of this convention, entitled
題は 「信仰によって
強くなりましょう！」です
“Become Powerful by Your Faith!”
A building constructed
with steel-reinforced concrete
鉄筋コンクリートで建てられた建物は
強い地震に持ちこたえることができます
can withstand powerful earthquakes.
A tree with strong, deep roots
地中の深くに根を張った頑丈な木は
can remain standing
in the face of many powerful storms.
嵐に何度遭っても
倒れることがありません
厳しいトレーニングを受けて
自分を鍛え上げた運動選手は
An athlete made powerful by rigorous training
can successfully complete a decathlon
デカスロンと呼ばれる10種目競技を
—a ten-event athletic contest.
最後まで行うことができます
Well, just as a building, a tree,
建物がしっかり立ち
木や運動選手が強くなれるように
and an athlete can be powerful,
エホバに仕える私たちも
we as Jehovah’s people
can be powerful by means of our faith.
信仰によって強くなることができます
And we will discuss during this talk
how faith
この話では 宇宙で最も強力な力である
—a product of holy spirit,
the most powerful force in the universe—
聖なる力が生み出す信仰によって
どのように強くなれるかを学びます
can reinforce, or fortify, us
for any (and I mean any)
信仰によって強くなっていれば
どんな問題や試練や誘惑も
test, trial, or temptation
乗り越えることができます
that comes our way.
自分にはあまり体力がないとか
Now, even though
we may not feel powerful physically
精神面で強くないと思うかもしれません
or emotionally,
でも信仰があれば
エホバとの絆が強まります
our faith can make us powerful spiritually.
エホバとの絆が強いことは
And spiritual power is much more valuable
体力があることや精神面で
強いことよりもはるかに大切です
than physical or emotional power.
エホバとの絆が強ければ
アブラハムのようになれます
With spiritual power, we can be like Abraham.
Please go to Romans chapter 4,
ローマ 4章を開いてみましょう
and notice what was said about Abraham,
beginning in verse number 18:
アブラハムについて述べられています
18節から読みます
「かないそうにない希望でしたが
“Although beyond hope, yet based on hope,
それでもアブラハムは希望に
基づいて信仰を持ちました
“he had faith that he would become
the father of many nations
『あなたの子孫も星のように
多くなる』と言われた通り
“according to what had been said:
‘So your offspring will be.’
多くの国の人々の
父祖となることを信じたのです
“And although he did not grow weak in faith,
自分の体がすでに死んだも同然である
（およそ100歳だった）ことや
“he considered his own body,
now as good as dead
“(since he was about 100 years old),
サラが子供を産めなくなって
いることを考えましたが
“as well as the deadness
of the womb of Sarah.
信仰は弱くなりませんでした
“But because of the promise of God,
神の約束があったので 信仰が欠けて
ふらつくということはなく
“he did not waver in a lack of faith;
“but he [now notice]
かえって［次に注目してください］
“became powerful by his faith,
信仰によって強くなりました
“giving God glory and being fully convinced
そして 神をたたえ
“that what He [Jehovah] had promised
神が約束を必ず果たされる
ということを確信していました」
He [Jehovah] was also able to do.”
Even though almost 100 years old
アブラハムは100歳近くに
なっていました
—and Abraham likely
would have been frail physically
体力も衰え 感情面でも弱さを
感じることがあったかもしれません
and emotionally weak at times—
でも 信仰によって強くなりました
his faith made him powerful.
In fact, his faith made him so powerful
信仰によって強くなっていたので
この驚くような約束を心から信じました
that he believed this extraordinary promise
with all his heart
90歳近くになっていた妻サラから
—that his almost 90-year-old wife, Sarah,
息子が生まれるという約束です
would give birth to a son
and that it would definitely come true.
それを固く信じました
And even though that promise
was unbelievable from a human standpoint,
普通に考えたらとても
信じられないような約束でしたが
he had no doubt whatsoever.
アブラハムは少しも疑いませんでした
Well, likewise, if our faith
makes us powerful,
私たちも信仰によって強くなるなら
we will fully believe
all of Jehovah’s promises
エホバの約束がどんなに
驚くようなものでも
その全てを全く信じることができます
no matter how extraordinary they may seem.
We will do so without doubting whatsoever.
約束の実現を決して
疑うことはありません
But now think about this comparison
to Abraham:
アブラハムと比較して考えてみましょう
An older, frail,
chronically ill servant of Jehovah
例えば 高齢で体力がなく
病気のクリスチャンは
弱く見えるかもしれません
may seem weak,
でも 外見だけで
判断することはできません
but outward appearance can be very deceptive.
もしその人が信仰によって
強くなっているなら
If that one has been empowered by faith,
then he is truly strong, just like Abraham.
アブラハムのように
本当に強い人といえます
この素晴らしい大会の目的は
私たちの信仰を強めることです
And this wonderful convention
was designed to fortify our faith
強い信仰があれば
so that it will empower us to be so strong
どんな問題や試練や誘惑に遭うとしても
that we’ll be able to endure
whatever test, trial, and temptation
それを乗り越えることができます
comes against us.
そして どんなものも
And there will actually be no breaking point
私たちの忠誠を
打ち砕くことはできません
to our integrity.
では 大会の話や
素晴らしいドラマによって
But now let’s talk about how each day
of our convention
and our outstanding drama
私たちの信仰はどのように
強くなったでしょうか
have strengthened our faith.
まず1日目です
First, let’s talk about Friday.
The day’s theme was a quote from Luke 17:5:
その日の主題は
ルカ 17:5から取られていました
「さらに信仰を与えてください」
“Give us more faith.”
Now, these were the humble words
of Jesus’ apostles
イエスの使徒たちの謙遜な言葉です
使徒たちはもっと信仰が
必要であることを認め
who recognized their need for more faith,
「信仰を与えてください」と言いました
and they were humbly pleading for such.
私たちも同感です
Well, we feel the same way, don’t we?
We know we need more faith,
もっと信仰が必要です
「信仰を与えてください」
と謙遜に祈ります
and we humbly ask Jehovah for it.
ではエホバは祈りに答え
But now the question is,
Will Jehovah answer our pleas for more faith?
さらに信仰を与えてくれるでしょうか
もちろんです
Yes, he will.
And Friday revealed
some of the ways Jehovah answers
1日目には エホバがどんな方法で
そうした祈りに答えてくれるのかを
学ぶことができました
our humble plea for more faith.
As illuminated on Friday,
1日目に学んだように
エホバが私たちに信仰を与えるために
使っている本が2冊あります
Jehovah gives us faith
primarily by means of two books
聖書と創造物です
—the Bible and the book of creation.
The first symposium showed
how the Bible builds faith
最初のシンポジウムでは
聖書を学ぶと次のものに信仰を
持てることが取り上げられました
in God’s existence;
it builds faith in itself,
that it’s the Word of God;
神の存在 聖書そのもの
it builds faith in God’s moral standards;
神の道徳基準
そして私たちに対する神の愛です
and it builds faith in God’s love for us.
But now we ask that first part,
では 神の存在に対する信仰は
どのように強まりますか
How does the Bible build faith
in God’s existence?
1つの点として 聖書の中には
納得のいく説明があります
Well, for one thing, within its pages,
it gives us common sense,
reasoning from scriptures
例えばヘブライ 3:4です
such as Hebrews 3:4.
And do you know what that says?
どんな聖句でしょうか こうあります
It says: “Of course,
「言うまでもなく 家は全て
誰かによって造られるのであり
“every house is constructed by someone,
but the one
who constructed all things is God.”
全てのものを造ったのは神です」
Now, you could never convince
any sane person
美しい家を指さして
「あの家は設計者がいなくて
ひとりでに建ったんです」と言っても
that a beautiful house
designed and built itself.
信じる人はいないでしょう
Even more so,
そうであれば
it should not be possible
to convince any rational person
星や森や生き物など
自然界に見られる
美しいものについてはなおのこと
that all the beautiful creations around us
ひとりでにできたなどとは
考えられないはずです
just designed and built themselves
or that they’re the product of blind chance.
偶然できたとは考えないでしょう
設計が見られるところには
Where there is design,
there is always a designer.
必ず設計者がいるはずです
例えで考えましょう
Now let’s illustrate this:
How many times
ニューヨーク市の完璧な地図を
天井に描くとします
would you have to throw
black paint from a can
ちょっと変わった方法を使います
onto a white ceiling
黒いペンキを缶から天井に
ただぶちまけるのです
until you produced
a perfect map of New York City,
それを何度も繰り返します
飛び散ったペンキで詳細な
地図ができるまでやります
until the paint particles scattered
accurately identifying all of the streets,
全ての道や高速道路やトンネルや
橋や陸橋や建物もです
the highways, the tunnels, the bridges,
the overpasses, and the landmarks
それぞれの名前もです
and correctly named each one?
Well, you could do that
for billions of times,
何億回やっても構いません
でも いくら頑張っても
完璧な地図などできないでしょう
and never would you produce
a perfect map of New York City.
ここでちょっとユーモアを
加えさせてください
Now to add a little humor:
Let’s say you tried doing this
for 100 billion years, and you get excited.
頑張ってこれを
1000億年続けたとしましょう
なんと ついに地図ができました！
You finally got a city map.
But, oh, no!
でも よく見ると
ニューヨーク市ではなく
It’s not New York City;
it’s Warwick, New York.
小さな田舎町
ウォーウィックの地図です
これではやり直しです
Now you’ve got to start all over,
going for that map of New York City.
ちゃんとニューヨーク市の
地図ができるまでです
I had to give you a little humor.
ご苦労さまです
考えてみてください
But think of this: One living human cell
人間の1つの細胞は
is much more complex,
ニューヨーク市の地図よりも
はるかに複雑で
intricately designed,
緻密に設計されています
than a map of New York City.
And one human body
人体は100兆個ほどの
細胞でできています
is made up of about 100 trillion
of such amazing cells
驚くほど複雑な細胞一つ一つが
all working together harmoniously.
調和よく機能しているのです
Well, in the second part,
how does the Bible build faith in itself
2つ目に 聖書を読むと
聖書そのものに対する信仰が
どのように強まりますか
—that it is the Word of God?
1つの点として 聖書の
アドバイスは全て役に立ち
Well, for one thing,
everything the Bible recommends
人間のアドバイスより
優れた結果を生み出します
works and brings superior results
子育てや結婚生活などに
役立つアドバイスがあります
—how to raise children,
how to have a happy marriage, and so forth.
考えてみてください
Think about it:
Humans simply aren’t smart enough
人間は いつも役立つアドバイスが
できるほど賢くはありません
to recommend only what works,
人間のアドバイスは 時代や
状況の変化と共に変わります
and their advice is constantly being revised
and updated, isn’t it?
Though written hundreds,
thousands, of years ago,
それに対し 何千年も前に
書かれた聖書のアドバイスは
the Bible has never needed to be revised.
変わることがありません
Yet, everything it recommends works.
全てのアドバイスが役に立ちます
It has to be from a higher source
than humans.
高い知恵を持つ方からの
ものであるに違いありません
3つ目に 聖書は神の道徳基準への
信仰をどのように強めますか
Well, in the third part, how does the Bible
build faith in God’s moral standards?
聖書は神の基準が何かを説明し
それに従うよう勧めています
Well, it tells us what they are.
It encourages us to obey them,
and when we do,
従うなら 体や心の健康
エホバとの友情を保てます
it protects us physically,
emotionally, and spiritually.
幸せになれます
健全な良心を持てます
We get happiness;
we get a good conscience;
we experience the benefits.
いいことずくめです
Thus, we don’t have to learn
the painful process
向こう見ずなことをやってみて
痛い思いをし
そこから学ぶという必要はありません
of trial and error.
There’s a saying
that “experience is the best teacher”
よく 「経験は最高の教師」
と言われます
これは間違いです
—completely wrong.
Experience is a school of hard knocks.
あえてつらいことを
経験する必要はありません
最高の教師はエホバです
Jehovah is the best Teacher.
“Jehovah is . . . making
the inexperienced one wise,”
詩編 19:7にはこうあります
「エホバ［は］経験の
浅い人を賢くする」
according to Psalm 19:7.
Well, in the fourth part, how does the Bible
4つ目に 聖書は神の愛への
信仰をどのように強めますか
build faith in God’s love for us?
The most powerful way is,
聖書を読むと エホバが初子のイエスを
it explains how Jehovah gave
his firstborn Son to die for us
私たちのために死ぬように
されたことが分かります
私たちの永遠の命のためです
so that we could have everlasting life.
ほとんどの人は何かを手放すとき
Now think about it:
What do most people give away
どんなものを手放しますか
if they give something away?
必要のないものや
なくても大丈夫なものです
Something they don’t need
or at least something they can do without.
でも エホバは一番
大切なものを与えました
But Jehovah gave at great cost,
大きな痛みを感じながらです
great pain to himself.
Evolution teaches
進化論は 私たちの先祖が
that our ancestors were apes.
類人猿だと教えています
もし 私たちのお父さんが
類人猿だとしたらどう思いますか
How could we feel happy and feel loved
thinking that an ape was our father?
愛されていると感じますか
でもうれしいことに 私たちの
本当のお父さんはエホバです
But our real Father, Jehovah,
is the personification of love.
愛の神です
But now, on Friday afternoon,
1日目の午後には 2つ目の
シンポジウムがありました
we had our second symposium,
創造物という本をいわば開きました
which opened the book of creation.
この本をよく調べると
And peering into this book
信仰が強まります
can empower our faith.
まず 星について取り上げた
最初の話を思い出しましょう
First, let’s talk about that first talk
that dealt with the stars.
Isaiah 40:26 tells us
イザヤ 40:26によると
that Jehovah created all of them
エホバは全ての星を造りました
そして「全ての星を名で呼」びます
and ‘he calls all of them by name.’
Now let’s ponder this for a moment:
ちょっと考えてみましょう
How long would it take you
天の川銀河にある星の名前を
to name just the stars
in the Milky Way galaxy
1秒に1つずつ挙げていったら
どれくらい時間がかかると思いますか
if you named one every second?
Joseph, Paul, Rachel, Sarah.
ヨセフ パウロ ラケル サラ
Well, scientists estimate
科学者たちによると
天の川銀河だけでも
that there are perhaps 400 billion stars
恐らく4000億個の星が
あると言われています
just in the Milky Way galaxy.
1秒に1個名前を挙げると
4000億秒かかります
So if you named one a second,
it would take you 400 billion seconds.
何年になりますか
Now, how long is that?
1万2684年です
Twelve thousand six hundred
and eighty four years
—more than twice the time that has passed
アダムが創造されてから今までの
2倍以上の時間です
since the creation of Adam.
それで終わりではありません
別の銀河もあります
And then you could go to the next galaxy.
And scientists estimate
科学者たちは 宇宙全体には
that there may be two trillion galaxies
in the universe.
2兆個の銀河があると考えています
天の川銀河には4000億個の
星があるということでしたが
That’s five times the number of galaxies
as our individual stars in the Milky Way.
その5倍の数の銀河が
あることになります
想像しただけでも気が遠くなります
Now, if you ponder that,
it will really give you a headache.
Yet, Jehovah created, sustains,
でもエホバは全ての星を創造し
制御し 名で呼びます
and calls every one of them by name.
話の中では エホバにそれができるなら
And the talk made the point
that if Jehovah can do that,
he will have no problem
remembering and recreating
記念の墓で眠っている
全ての人のことを記憶し
all those sleeping in the memorial tombs.
再創造することができる
はずだ と言われました
The second talk examined
the page in the book of creation
2つ目の話では 創造物という本の
海が取り上げられました
about the oceans.
海には大きな力があります
How powerful they are!
でも海を造った方ははるかに強力です
But the One who made them
is vastly more powerful.
And our powerful God
definitely can protect us now
強力な神エホバは
私たちを今も
and right through the great tribulation.
大患難の間も必ず守ってくれます
The third talk examined
the page in creation about the forests,
3つ目の話では
森が取り上げられました
森林には 自ら再生し回復するという
素晴らしい能力があることを学びました
and it was discussed how forests
have the amazing ability
to repair and renew themselves.
And the point was made that the One
who has the wisdom to create such forests
そのような森林を創造する
知恵を持つ神であれば
surely knows how to undo all the damage
人間が地球に与えたダメージを
全て元通りにすることができるはずだ
と述べられました
that man has done to the planet Earth.
4つ目の話では
水と風が取り上げられました
The fourth talk focused on wind and water,
話にあった通り エホバは昔
and it talked about how Jehovah
has in the past used wind and water
水と風を使いました
—and especially water in the form of hail—
特にひょうという形の水を使って
敵たちを滅ぼし
to defeat his enemies and deliver his people.
ご自分の民を救出しました
Well, he will use them again at Armageddon.
ハルマゲドンの時も
水や風を使うでしょう
The fifth talk took a glimpse
5つ目の話では美しい海の中をのぞき
into the fascinating world of sea creatures,
今地球で生きている一番大きな
生き物に注目しました
and we looked at the largest animal alive
on earth today
シロナガスクジラです
—the blue whale.
And what an appetite
大きな体を持つこのクジラは
食欲旺盛です
that blue whale has!
その話で見たビデオによると
It can eat, according to the video,
1日に何トンもの餌を食べます
tons of food every day.
でもエホバは養っています
Yet, Jehovah feeds it.
もしそれができるのであれば
Now, if he can do that,
王国をいつも第一にしている私たちを
can he not feed and care for us,
養い 世話してくれるのでは
ないでしょうか
if we continue to seek first the Kingdom?
Well, our faith was strengthened
エホバにはその意志と能力がある
という信仰が強まりました
that he can and he will.
最後の話では 素晴らしい
人体に注目しました
The last talk examined our amazing bodies.
人体には驚くような能力があります
As discussed, it’s miraculous
けがをしても 自己修復能力によって
回復します
how our bodies heal
and repair themselves when damaged.
Now think of this:
If you damage, scrape, or dent your car,
車は傷が付いたりへこんだりしたら
自己修復しますか
しません
does it heal itself?
Hardly!
もし私たちがあざを作ったり
けがをしたり 骨折したりしても
What if every time we bruised, scraped,
or damaged our body
治らなかったらどうなりますか
it just stayed that way?
In a short time,
we’d get to looking pretty rough.
短期間のうちに目も当てられない
姿になるでしょう
But the God who made our bodies
in this miraculous way
人体に自己修復能力を組み込んだ神は
新しい世界で全ての病気を治し
certainly can heal all infirmities,
reverse aging,
老化を逆転させ
and prevent sickness in his new world.
病気にかからないように
してくれるでしょう
And he has promised to do that.
エホバはそう約束しています
3つ目のシンポジウムでは
Well, the third symposium
信仰を強める主な本 聖書に
再び注意を向けました
went back to our main book that builds faith
—the Bible.
And we discussed those
信仰の強い人たちに注目し
who acquired strong faith,
彼らがどのように信仰を
強めたかを学びました
and we discussed how they did it.
彼らは信仰の欠けた人たちに
囲まれていましたが
And even though their contemporaries
were faithless,
信仰をいっそう強めました
they developed this faith.
信仰を強めるたくさんの
手本に注目しました
Well, our faith was empowered
as we discussed Abel, Enoch, Noah,
アベル エノク ノア モーセ
イエスの弟子たちです
Moses, and Jesus’ disciples,
and we became more determined than ever
信仰の欠けた人ではなく
to imitate these faithful ones
信仰の強い人に倣いたいという
願いがいっそう強まりました
and not their faithless contemporaries.
私たちも強い信仰を示せます
And we know we can be successful
because we have the same Father, Helper,
同じお父さん 同じ助け手がいます
Supplier of holy spirit as they had.
エホバは私たちにも
聖なる力を与えてくれます
このように 1日目の
3つのシンポジウムでは
Yes, our three symposiums on Friday
clearly showed us
エホバが私たちの信仰を強めるために
使うものに注目しました
that Jehovah answers our pleas for more faith
by means of two books
2冊の本 聖書と創造物です
—the Bible and the book of creation.
ここでドラマについて
ちょっと考えましょう
But regarding our drama, we ask,
さらに信仰を与えてほしい
というダニエルの願いに
How did Jehovah answer
Daniel’s pleas for more faith?
エホバはどう答えましたか
1つとして 聖なる書物を与えました
Well, one way was
he gave Daniel his written Word.
ドラマの中で ダニエルの父親は
In the drama, if you recall,
Daniel’s father gave him a scroll
ダニエルに巻物を渡しました
that he regularly referred to.
ダニエルはいつもそれを読んでいました
その巻物に気付きましたか
Did you recognize that scroll?
The scroll depicted in the drama
ドラマに出てきた巻物は
is known today as Psalm 27.
今でいう詩編 27編です
When enemies tried to discredit Daniel,
敵たちがダニエルの預言をあざけった時
we saw him reflect on Psalm 27:11, 12,
which says in part:
ダニエルは詩編 27:11, 12を
思い返しました
“Do not hand me over to my adversaries,
こうあります 「敵対者の手に
私を渡さないでください
“for false witnesses
have risen up against me,
偽りを語る証人が立ち上がり
私を激しく脅してきます」
and they threaten me with violence.”
When he was threatened with execution,
ダニエルは処刑されそうになった時
we saw him reflect
詩編 27:7-9を
思い返していました
on Psalm 27:7-9,
こうあります
which says in part:
「あなたは私を助ける方
“You are my helper;
“do not forsake me or leave me,
私の救いの神 見捨てないでください
my God of salvation.”
放っておかないでください」
How those verses
ダニエルはこの聖句を読んで
would have bolstered Daniel’s faith!
信仰をとても強められたに
違いありません
ダニエルが実際にこの聖句を
思い巡らしたかどうか
Of course, we cannot say for sure
that Daniel reflected
on those specific verses,
はっきりしたことは言えません
but the Bible does reveal that Daniel’s faith
でも聖書からはっきり言えるのは
ダニエルが聖句を読んで
信仰を強めた ということです
indeed was strengthened by the Scriptures.
ご存じのように ダニエルは
聖書の預言をよく調べました
And we know that Daniel
was a keen student of Bible prophecy.
He even said of himself at Daniel 9:2:
ダニエル 9:2でこう言っています
“I, Daniel, discerned by the books
「私ダニエルは書物
［聖なる書物］を調べ ⋯⋯
年数を知った」
[that is, the sacred books]
the number of years.”
And then he talks about the desolation
(restoration) of Jerusalem
つまり エルサレムの荒廃が
「70年」続くということです
—“namely, 70 years.”
ではエホバは 私たちにもさらに
信仰を与えてくれますか
But now we ask, Will Jehovah answer
our pleas for more faith?
Most definitely he will.
必ず与えてくれます
例えば 私たちの信仰を強めるために
And one outstanding way he has done this
聖書の預言を与えてくれています
is by providing us with Bible prophecy.
Prophecies in the book of Daniel alone
have helped millions
非常に多くの人がダニエル書の
預言を調べただけで
強い信仰を持つようになりました
to build rock-solid faith.
For example, the fulfilled prophecies
例えば 北の王と南の王の預言が
regarding the king of the north
and the king of the south
どのように実現したかを考えると
信仰がとても強まります
have been very faith-strengthening.
In fact, let’s review the video on this topic
この預言について 5月の
マンスリープログラムの
ケニス･クック兄弟の話を
もう一度聞いてみましょう
that appeared in Brother Kenneth Cook’s
May broadcast.
ビデオをお楽しみください
Enjoy this powerful video.
Daniel received a prophecy
ダニエルは2人の王が
敵対することを預言しました
about the coming of two rivals:
“the king of the north”
「北の王」と「南の王」です
and “the king of the south.”
How has it been fulfilled?
どのように実現してきましたか
1800年代後半 ドイツ帝国が
北の王になりました
In the late 1800’s, the German Empire
became the king of the north.
That government brought
ドイツ政府は 「力と勇気を奮い起こし
大きな軍隊で南の王を攻め」ました
its “power and . . . heart
“against the king of the south
with a large army.”
世界で2番目の規模の
海軍を持っていました
In fact, its navy was
the second largest on earth.
では 誰が南の王になりましたか
Who became the king of the south?
軍事同盟を結んだ英国と米国です
The alliance between Britain
and the United States.
第1次世界大戦中 「非常に
強大な軍隊で」戦いました
He fought during World War I
“with an exceedingly large
and mighty army.”
そして 北の王を「押し流［し］」
「打ち負か［し］」ました
He “swept away” and “humbled”
the king of the north.
But that was not the end
でも 北の王は活動を
やめたわけではありません
of the king of the north.
He turned his attention to and then hurled
「聖なる契約に」注意を向け
「糾弾」を浴びせます
“denunciations against the holy covenant.”
そして 「日ごとの犠牲」
を除き去ります
He removed “the constant feature”
by limiting the freedom of God’s people
神の民が伝道を行う自由を制限し
to preach,
天に行くよう選ばれたクリスチャンと
その仲間たちを大勢投獄し
imprisoning many,
and even killing hundreds
of God’s anointed ones
殺すことさえしたのです
and their fellow workers.
After Germany was defeated in World War II,
ドイツが第2次世界大戦で敗れた後
the Soviet Union
ソビエト連邦が北の王になりました
became the king of the north.
It worked with the king of the south
北の王は南の王と手を組み
to “put in place the disgusting thing
「荒廃をもたらす極めて
不快なものを据え」ました
that causes desolation”
—the United Nations.
国際連合です
1900年代の初めから
Beginning in the early 1900’s,
ソビエト政府は連邦内の
宗教を排除しようとしました
the Soviet government tried to eliminate
religion in the lands under its control,
こうして 「自分の父祖たちの神を
無視」するという預言が実現しました
fulfilling the words
that he would “show no regard
for the God of his fathers.”
天の神ではなく
「要塞の神」をたたえたのです
He gave glory, not to the God of heaven,
but “to the god of fortresses.”
預言通り 北の王は南の王に軍事力
を行使し 「彼と押し合い」ました
As prophesied,
he used this military might
against the king of the south
by engaging “with him in a pushing.”
英米同盟とソビエト連邦は
覇権争いを続け
Anglo-America competed
with the Soviet Union
for world domination,
世界中の戦争や紛争に関わりました
fighting in and supporting wars
and political struggles around the globe.
1991年にソビエト連邦が崩壊した後
After the Soviet Union collapsed in 1991,
it was unclear who would fill the role
of the king of the north.
誰が北の王になるのか
はっきり分かりませんでした
しばらくの間 神の民は
伝道や崇拝を自由に行えました
For a time, God’s people there
had been able to preach
and worship peacefully.
しかし近年 ロシアとそれを支持する
国々は 南の王を押し返しています
But in recent years, Russia and its allies
have pushed back at the king of the south.
Both kings have accused each other
どちらの王も相手のサイバー攻撃
を非難しています
of destructive cyber and economic attacks.
北の王が攻撃しているのは
南の王だけではありません
But the king of the north has not limited
his attacks to the king of the south.
As foretold, he also entered
預言通り クリスチャンの
活動領域である
“into the land of the Decoration”
「『美しい地』にも入［って］」います
—our realm of spiritual activity.
ロシア当局は今も真の崇拝への
攻撃を続けています
Today, Russian authorities continue
to attack true worship.
私たちはそのような迫害を
予期していました
We expect such persecution,
そしてそれが終わることも知っています
but we also expect it to end.
私たちの王イエス･キリストは
どんな人間の政府よりも強力な方です
Our King, Jesus Christ,
is more powerful than any human government.
イエスは間もなく
北の王と南の王だけでなく
Soon he will destroy
not only the kings of the north and the south
全ての敵を滅ぼします
but all of his enemies,
そして 神を愛する人たちを
救出するのです
and he will deliver God’s loyal people.
What a powerful video!
本当に励みとなるビデオです
ダニエルの預言が正確に
実現してきたことを知って
Has the unerring accuracy of those prophecies
あなたの信仰は強まりましたか
strengthened your faith?
We’re confident that it has.
きっとそうだと思います
And we’re absolutely convinced
that the rest of that prophecy,
私たちの救出を含め
ダニエルの預言の残りの部分も
including our deliverance,
必ず実現すると確信できます
will be fulfilled.
キリストは間もなく神の民を守り
Christ soon will defend God’s people
and bring an end
to this entire wicked system.
今の邪悪な体制全体を終わらせます
May all of us continue to study
この預言や他の預言について
これからも深く学びましょう
these and other prophecies.
そうすれば 賢くて 強力で
If we do, our faith
in our wise, our all-powerful,
our loving Father
愛情深いお父さんエホバに対する
信仰が強まるに違いありません
will definitely be strengthened.
But now let’s move to Saturday’s program,
では2日目のプログラムを
振り返りましょう
which had the theme taken from Jude 3:
主題はユダ 3節から取られていました
「信仰のために真剣に戦う」
“Put up a hard fight for the faith.”
The symposium
“Successful Fighters for the Faith”
「信仰のために立派に戦っている
人たち」というシンポジウムでは
showed that many who do not have a spouse
大勢の独身の兄弟姉妹や
and many whose spouse
is not yet serving Jehovah
夫や妻がまだ信者ではない人たちが
信仰の戦いで勝利を
収めていることを学びました
are winning their fight for the faith.
And we warmly commend
そのような兄弟姉妹は 本当に
素晴らしい努力を払っています
you dear, beloved ones.
The baptism discourse
encouraged new disciples
バプテスマの話では 新しい兄弟姉妹が
これからも信仰を強めるよう
励まされました
to continue strengthening their faith,
and we warmly welcome
all newly baptized ones.
バプテスマを受けた皆さん全てを
温かく歓迎します
エホバは皆さんを愛しています
Jehovah loves you very much.
統治体も皆さんを愛しています
The Governing Body loves you very much.
兄弟姉妹も皆さんを愛しています
Your brothers and sisters love you very much.
今回皆さんを 固い絆で結ばれた家族に
お迎えできたことをうれしく思います
And we’re so happy to have you join us
in our united family
これからも信仰のために
一緒に戦いましょう
of intense fighters for the faith.
2日目午後のシンポジウムでは
The two afternoon symposiums
helped us to analyze
how we can show our faith
信仰を表す方法を
さらに学ぶことができました
時間やエネルギーや
持っているものを使って
by giving of our time,
energy, and material things
王国の活動に参加し
他の人を助けることができます
to advance the Kingdom work
and to help others.
具体的に どんな方法が
取り上げられたでしょうか
And we discussed some specific things
that we may be able to do.
For example, learn a new language,
例えば 新たな言語を学ぶこと
必要の大きな所に引っ越すこと
move and serve where the need is greater,
王国福音伝道者のための学校で学ぶこと
apply for the School
for Kingdom Evangelizers,
建設プロジェクトに参加すること
assist with a building project,
「取り分け」たものをエホバに
差し出すことなどです
and “set something aside” for Jehovah’s work.
The talk “Put Up a Hard Fight for the Faith!”
「信仰のために真剣に戦いましょう！」
という話はどうでしたか
reminded us that as is true in all fights
どんな戦いについても言えることですが
私たちにも敵がいます
—in our fight—
we have enemies.
For one thing, we must reject apostate lies
例えば 背教者のうそや
他の反対者の作り話を
退けなければなりません
and the false stories of other opposers,
彼らは疑念を生じさせ
which are designed to sow doubt
and weaken faith.
信仰を弱めようとしているからです
Satan is very skilled
サタンはネガティブで不正確な情報や
うそを巧みに使います
at using innuendo, half-truths, and lies.
So it’s not surprising that the news media
ですから メディアが
エホバの組織に関する
ネガティブで不正確な情報や
—which is often manipulated by apostates,
clergymen, and other opposers—
うそを使うとしても
驚くには当たりません
likewise often employs innuendo,
そうしたメディアは 背教者や聖職者や
half-truths, and lies
他の反対者に操作されていることが
少なくありません
against Jehovah’s organization.
Think about this:
Faith is a product of holy spirit.
信仰は 聖なる力が生み出すものです
It’s a provision from Jehovah
to strengthen us,
私たちを強めるために
エホバが与えてくださるものです
それに対し疑念は
whereas doubt
悪魔が私たちを
弱めるために使う道具です
is a tool of the Devil designed to weaken us.
Do you recall how Satan approached Eve?
サタンはエバにこのように
話し掛けました
「あなたたちは庭園の全ての木の実を
“Is it really so
that God said you must not eat
from every tree of the garden?”
食べてはならない と
神が言ったのは本当ですか」
「本当ですか」
‘Is that really so?’
なぜこんな言い方をしましたか
Why did he present it that way?
To plant doubt
疑念を抱かせ
「信仰を失」わせるためです
and ‘shipwreck her faith,’ and he succeeded.
サタンは成功しました
Well, likewise, if we’re not careful,
私たちも注意しないと信仰を
失ってしまうかもしれません
doubt can shipwreck our faith.
でも 強い信仰があれば 疑念が
心に入り込むことはないでしょう
But strong faith
keeps doubt out of our hearts and minds.
では 背教者について
もう少し考えてみましょう
But now, in talking just a little bit more
about apostates,
背教者があなたの家のドアを
ノックしてこう言うとします
what if an apostate knocked
at your front door and said,
「中に入れてくれませんか
“I’d like to come into your home,
I’d like to sit down with you,
一緒に座って私たちの
考えを聞いてください」
and I’d like to teach you
some apostate ideas”?
そう言われたらどうしますか
すぐに追い払うのではないでしょうか
Why, you would immediately
get rid of him, wouldn’t you?
You would send him down the highway.
さっさと帰ってもらうはずです
But now think of this:
What if that same apostate
では同じ背教者が別の方法で
入ってこようとしたらどうしますか
tries to come into your home
by means of the television
テレビやコンピューターからです
or computer?
Well, hopefully, we reject him
もちろん そのようなときにも
きっぱりと退けたいと思います
just as decisively.
ヨハネ第二 10節にはこうあります
Second John 10 says:
“If anyone comes to you
and does not bring this teaching,
「キリストの教えに従わない人が
あなたたちの所に来たら
[never] receive him into your homes”
家に迎え入れてはなりません」
—that would mean not through the front door,
玄関に来た場合も
テレビやコンピューターを
通して来た場合も同じです
not through the television, or computer.
残念なことにこう考えて
しまった人がいます
Sadly, though, some have reasoned foolishly:
「この背教者の言うことを
テレビやコンピューターで見たり
‘If I listen to this apostate
on television or the computer
本で読んだりすれば
‘or perhaps read his book,
‘I’ll recognize how wrong he is.
その間違いがはっきり分かるはずだ
信仰も強まる
‘It’ll build up my faith.
‘And if I ever encounter this teaching
in the ministry,
伝道で同じようなことを言われた時に
上手に説明できるように
なるかもしれない」
I’ll better be able to refute it.’
Well, that is foolish thinking indeed.
これは本当に愚かな考え方です
That would be like reasoning,
こう考えるのと同じです
‘If I eat stinky, rotten, food
from a garbage can,
「ゴミ箱にある腐った食べ物を食べたら
今後 体に悪い食べ物を
見分ける助けになるだろう」
‘it will really help me in the future
to recognize bad food.’
いい考えとは言えませんね
That’s not very good reasoning, is it?
背教者の有毒な考えで
心を養うべきではありません
Rather than feed our minds
poisonous, apostate ideas,
we read God’s Word daily
むしろ聖書を毎日読み
and strengthen and safeguard our faith.
信仰を強め 信仰を守りたいと思います
But now we ask, How did Daniel
では ダニエルは信仰のために
どのように戦いましたか
put up a hard fight for the faith?
1つの点として 妥協させようとする
圧力に抵抗しました
Well, for one thing, he resisted pressure
to compromise.
But can you imagine the pressure
he must have faced
王の美食とぶどう酒を勧められた時
when offered the king’s delicacies and wine?
それを断るのは
簡単ではなかったでしょう
How was he able to refuse?
ダニエルはどうしましたか
Well, for the answer,
let’s go to Daniel chapter 1, please,
ご一緒にダニエル 1章の
聖句を読んでみましょう
and let’s read verse number 8.
ダニエル 1:8です
ダニエル 1:8
Daniel 1:8: “But Daniel
“resolved in his heart
「しかしダニエルは
王の美食やぶどう酒で自分を
汚さないことを心に決めた
“that he would not defile himself
with the king’s delicacies
“or with the wine he drank.
“So he asked the principal court official
for permission
それで 自分を汚さずに済むよう
not to defile himself in this way.”
廷臣の長に許可を求めた」
So notice, in advance,
ダニエルは前もって
Daniel “resolved in his heart”
「心に決め」ていました
どうすべきかを決めていたのです
the course he was going to take.
And he did so because he was fully convinced
そして実際にそうしました
エホバの命令は全て
自分のためになる ということを
that whatever Jehovah had commanded
全く確信していたからです
was for his good.
私たちも信仰のために
真剣に戦わなければなりません
Well, like Daniel, we must put up
a hard fight for the faith.
Are you facing pressure right now
もしかしたらあなたは今
学校や職場や家庭で
—at school, at work, or even at home—
圧力を受けているかもしれません
to compromise?
If so, please don’t give up
もしそうなら 諦めないでください
and don’t give in.
決して妥協しないでください
Reflect on Daniel’s example,
ダニエルの手本を思い出し
信仰のために戦ってください
and fight for your faith.
エホバに従うと心に決めてください
Be resolved to obey Jehovah because doing so
エホバに従うのは常に正しいことです
is always the right thing,
and if you do, you will have no regrets.
エホバに従うなら
後悔することはありません
Pressure was also put on Daniel
by means of threats.
ダニエルは別の圧力も受けました
脅しです
But can you imagine how Daniel felt
when he became aware
ダニエルの気持ちを
想像してみてください
that his next prayer
could lead to his execution?
今度祈ったら
処刑されるかもしれないのです
What helped him to stay loyal?
何が助けになりましたか
Well, let’s go to Daniel chapter 6
ダニエル 6章を見て
答えを探しましょう
and get some help with that question.
Daniel chapter 6
ダニエル 6:10です
and, please, let’s read together
verse number 10:
よろしければご一緒に読んでみましょう
“But as soon as Daniel knew
「ダニエルは 法令に
署名がされたことを知ると
“that the decree had been signed,
すぐに自分の家に入った
“he went to his house,
“which had the windows of his roof chamber
open toward Jerusalem.
屋上の部屋の窓は
エルサレムに向かって開かれていた
“And three times a day
he got down on his knees
ダニエルは［次に注目してください］
“and prayed and offered praise
before his God,
それまでいつもしていた通り
日に3度ひざまずいて祈り
“[now notice] as he had regularly done
自分の神を賛美した」
prior to this.”
So Daniel knew what was right,
ダニエルは正しいことを
ためらわずに行いました
and he didn’t hesitate to do it,
and he was consistent in his worship.
崇拝を続けたのです
Daniel 6:16 tells us
ダニエル 6:16には
ダニエルが神に「常に
仕えてい［た］」とあります
that Daniel
was “continually serving” his God.
And The Watchtower {
「ものみの塔」の説明によると
「常に仕えている」と訳されている
元のアラム語の基本的な意味は
translated “continually serving”
basically means to “move in a circle,”
「円を描いて動く」です
which suggests continuity.
継続しているということです
And how well that describes
Daniel’s unbroken worship!
ダニエルは何があっても
崇拝をやめませんでした
円に終わりがないように
エホバを崇拝し続けたのです
See, there’s no end to a circle.
It’s unbroken, is it not?
Please watch the following dramatization
ここで 次のビデオをご覧ください
that depicts a brother
who faces a threat of being arrested.
ある兄弟が逮捕されそうになります
But by reflecting on Daniel’s example,
でもダニエルの手本を思い巡らし
エホバに仕え続けることができました
he is helped to continue serving Jehovah
with constancy
いつも通りにです
in the face
of this intimidating circumstance.
恐れを感じるような
状況でもそうしました
首都での混乱はまだ収まっていません
It’s still chaos in many parts of the city,
軍が出動し 新政府を支持しない人への
逮捕・拘束が続いています
with armed soldiers detaining and arresting
those not pledging support
of the new government.
Are we still going to the meeting tonight?
今晩は集会に行けるかしら？
I wanted to do what was best
妻と娘のことが心配だった
for my wife and daughter.
But a few of the elders
逮捕された長老たちもいる
have already been arrested.
もし私が逮捕されたら・・・
What if I was arrested?
家族はどうなるんだろう？
What would happen to my family?
まさか祈らないですよね？
You’re not going home to pray, are you?
私は窓辺で祈っている
I pray at my window three times a day,
1日3回 毎日だ
every day.
If I even appear to compromise,
もし 窓辺で祈るのをやめたら
みんなはどう思うだろう？
what would they think?
エホバは私の友だ
I know Jehovah.
And if I trust him,
エホバを信頼すれば 報いてくださる
he’ll reward me.
どのようにかは分からない
I don’t know how,
でも必ず
but he will.
祈ってほしい 私が信仰を貫けるように
Pray that I keep my faith
みんなが信仰を貫けるように
—that we all keep our faith—
どんなことがあっても
no matter how this ends.
聖書の教えははっきりしている
The Scriptures are clear.
仲間と集まることをやめてはいけない
We must continue to meet together,
even in small groups if necessary.
少人数になるかもしれないけど
Let’s just pray that whatever happens,
一緒にエホバに祈ろう
we have the strength to endure it.
何が起きても耐えられるように
Dear Jehovah God, please . . .
お父さん エホバ⋯⋯
Eventually, I was arrested.
私も逮捕されました
We miss you so much,
どうしているかな と
いつも思っています
but we’re very proud of you.
あなたのことだから
どんな試練に遭っても
We know whatever the outcome of your trial,
信仰を貫くと信じています
you’ll maintain your faith,
and so will we.
私たち2人も頑張ります
Were you scared?
怖かった？
怖かったよ
I was very scared,
でもそういうときに
エホバは助けてくれる
but Jehovah helps us when we’re scared.
I knew I would be OK
大丈夫
and that Jehovah
家族はエホバが守ってくれる
would take care of my family.
As was true of the brother in our video,
このビデオに出てきた兄弟と同様
私たちも迫害を受けます
we will be persecuted.
テモテ第二 3:12にあるように
Second Timothy 3:12 says:
“All those desiring to live
with godly devotion
「神への専心を貫き
キリスト･イエスに従って
生きようとする人は皆
“in association with Christ Jesus
will also be persecuted.”
同じように迫害を受けます」
たぶんとか恐らくとは
述べられていません
It didn’t say maybe, good chance, probably
「迫害を受けます」と断言されています
—‘will be persecuted.’
It’s guaranteed.
But like our brother in the video,
ビデオに出てきた兄弟のように
迫害を受けたら
when persecuted,
let’s reflect on Daniel’s example
ダニエルの手本を思い出し
and let’s fight for our faith.
信仰のために戦いましょう
And then let’s pray,
confident that our God
エホバに祈ってください
エホバはどんな敵たちよりも強いのです
is always mightier than our enemies.
Let’s be like young David
when he went out to meet Goliath.
ゴリアテと戦った
若いダビデに倣いましょう
ダビデは全体像を見ていました
Now, David saw the big picture, didn’t he?
Sure, he saw how big Goliath was,
巨人ゴリアテを見ていましたが
全体像を見ていたので
but in the big picture,
ゴリアテがちっぽけな存在で
あることを知っていました
he saw how puny Goliath was
compared to his almighty God, Jehovah.
全能の神エホバと比べて見ていたのです
In a unique way, Daniel also experienced
ダニエルもエホバがどれほど
強力な方かを実感しました
how mighty Jehovah is
ライオンの穴に投げ込まれた時です
when he was thrown into the lions’ pit.
Jehovah sent an angel
to shut the mouths of those lions.
エホバは天使を送って
ライオンの口をふさぎました
考えてみてください ライオンは
空腹だったに違いありません
Now, think about it: Those lions
obviously were very hungry
because a little bit later
when people were thrown in there,
少し後に投げ込まれた人たちは
穴の底に落ちる前に
食べられてしまったからです
they were consumed
before they hit the bottom of the pit.
So they were very hungry,
空腹なライオンにとって ダニエルは
おいしそうなごちそうに見えたでしょう
and Daniel would have looked
like a tasty morsel.
でもライオンは どんなに頑張っても
But no matter how hard they tried,
ダニエルに対して口を開けて
those lions couldn’t get their mouths open
襲い掛かることはできませんでした
to harm Daniel.
Daniel also set a good example
ダニエルは別の手本も示しています
in remaining hopeful despite old age
高齢で体力が弱ってからも
前向きな見方を保ちました
and infirmities.
But can you imagine how Daniel felt
when he was almost 100 years old
ダニエルが100歳近くの時
多くのユダヤ人は懐かしい
故国ユダに戻りました
and many Jews left
for their beloved homeland, Judah,
でもダニエルは一緒に行けませんでした
and he was unable to go with them?
では 前向きな見方を持つ上で
何が助けになりましたか
But what helped him to keep his hope alive?
Well, let’s go to Daniel chapter 10, please.
ご一緒にダニエル 10章を
見てみましょう
Let’s see one thing that helped Daniel.
何が助けになったでしょうか
In Daniel chapter 10 and beginning
in verse 18, Daniel says:
ダニエル 10:18からです
ダニエルはこう言っています
「人のような姿の者は再び私に触れて
力づけてくれた
“The one who looked like a man
touched me again
“and strengthened me.
そしてこう言った 『大切な人よ
恐れることはありません
“Then he said: ‘Do not be afraid,
O very precious man.
あなたに平和がありますように
“‘May you have peace.
“Be strong, yes, be strong.’
勇気を出し 強くありなさい』
“As he spoke with me I was strengthened
彼が話しているうちに
私は力づけられ こう言った
“and I said: ‘Let my lord speak,
『どうぞお話しください あなたは
私を力づけてくださいました』」
for you have strengthened me.’”
So through an angel, Jehovah reassured Daniel
エホバは天使を通して
ダニエルが大切な人で
that he was precious
and still very useful to Him.
ご自分にとって非常に有用な
存在であることを伝えました
Well, Daniel accepted
the encouragement, didn’t he?
ダニエルはとても力づけられました
And thereafter, Jehovah
gave him a thrilling prophecy
その後エホバはダニエルに
北の王と南の王に関する
about the king of the north
and the king of the south, which he recorded
わくわくするような預言を書かせました
私たちのためにです
for our benefit.
高齢で体力が弱っていましたが
この大切な人は
Although old and infirm, this precious man
was still very useful to Jehovah.
エホバにとって有用な存在でした
Please watch the following dramatization
どうぞ次のビデオをご覧ください
in which an older brother who feels helpless
ある高齢の兄弟は
少しがっかりしていましたが
reflects on how the angel reassured Daniel.
天使に励まされた
ダニエルのことを思い返します
時が過ぎるのは早いものです
It all went by so quickly
—pioneering,
開拓奉仕
外国語での奉仕
foreign language,
巡回奉仕
circuit work.
There was even a time
少し前までは 私が高齢の人たちを
励ましていました
that I was the one encouraging older ones.
あの頃が本当に懐かしい
I miss those days so much.
But now I’m the one in a nursing home.
今では私が世話を受けている
Sometimes I feel like I have
もうできることが何もないように
感じることがある
nothing left to offer.
O Daniel,
大切な人ダニエル
you very precious man.
私は遣わされてきました
I have been sent to you.
恐れることはありません
Do not be afraid, Daniel.
あなたが謙遜になろうと
心に決めた最初の日から
Your words have been heard
from the first day you gave your heart
祈りは聞かれています
to understanding.
I have no strength.
もう力が出ません
There’s no breath left in me.
息をするのも大変です
大切な人ダニエル
恐れることはありません
Do not be afraid, O very precious man.
May you have peace.
大丈夫です
Be strong.
Be strong!
勇気を出してください
Happy is the one who keeps in expectation.
待ち続ける人は幸せです！
最後まで進んでいきなさい
Go on to the end.
You will rest, but you will stand up
あなたは休みますが 日々の終わりに
for your lot at the end of the days.
報いを受けるために立ち上がります
Hey, just checking on you.
こんにちは 調子はどうですか
Do you have a minute?
ちょっと時間ある？
見せたいものがあるんだ
There’s something I’ve been wanting
to share with you.
OK, sure.
いいですよ
エホバは私のことを
大切に思っておられる
Yes, Jehovah does remember me,
and I still have much to offer.
できることはまだまだある
That was a very touching video indeed!
本当に感動的なビデオでした
But now we ask, Do you have infirmities
あなたは健康上の問題のために
that keep you from doing
what you would like to do?
できることが限られていますか
If so, reflect on Daniel’s example
もしそうなら ダニエルの
手本を思い出し
and accept Jehovah’s reassurance.
エホバから力を得ましょう
And remember that what you used to do
あなたが以前に行ったことを
is still viewed as valuable to Jehovah.
エホバは今でも大切に思っています
決して忘れたりはされません
He will not forget it.
そしてあなたが今していることは
And your present acts of faithfulness,
たとえ小さくても エホバにとって
とても大切です
even if small,
are very precious to him.
We entreat all of you:
皆さんにお勧めします
Whether young or old,
若くても高齢でも
ダニエルに倣ってください
like Daniel, do not stop
信仰のために真剣に戦い続けてください
putting up a hard fight for the faith.
では3日目のプログラムを
振り返りましょう
But now let’s talk about today’s program,
マタイ 21:21に基づく主題でした
which has the theme taken from Matthew 21:21:
“If you have faith . . . , it will happen.”
「信仰を持[つ]なら ⋯⋯
そうなります」
In the morning, we enjoyed
the faith-strengthening symposium
午前には 信仰を強める
シンポジウムを楽しみました
“Imitate Women of Strong Faith!”
「強い信仰を持つ女性から
学ぶ」という主題です
And in each of the eight parts,
8部から成るこのシンポジウムに
出てきた女性たちは
the exemplary women of faith
who were discussed
強い信仰を示して
faced mountainlike obstacles.
山のような問題を
乗り越えることができました
Sarah had to leave a comfortable lifestyle
サラは 快適な生活を後にして
遊牧生活をしました
for a nomadic lifestyle,
そして何年も子供ができませんでした
and for many years, she suffered barrenness.
Rahab had to take decisive action
—risk her life—
ラハブは命を懸けて
思い切った行動を取りました
イスラエルの偵察者たちを守り
神の民の側に付いたのです
to protect the Israelite spies
and take a stand with God’s people.
Thereafter, she had to give up
an immoral lifestyle.
またその後 不道徳な
生き方をやめました
Hannah continued to serve Jehovah
ハンナは何年も子供ができず
while enduring many years of barrenness
and harassment from Peninnah.
ペニンナから嫌がらせを受けましたが
エホバに仕え続けました
The captive Israelite girl
イスラエルの少女は
was forcibly separated from her family
シリアの略奪者たちによって
無理やり家族から引き離され
by Syrian marauders
捕らわれの身になりました
それでも エホバについて
恐れることなく
but nevertheless continued
to fearlessly witness
to others about Jehovah.
他の人に伝え続けました
マリアは難しい務めを受け入れました
Mary accepted the difficult assignment
of giving birth to, caring for,
神の子を産み 養い
育て上げるという務めです
and training God’s Son.
フェニキア人の女性は邪悪な天使に
取りつかれた娘を治してほしいと
The Phoenician woman
courageously and persistently
sought help from Jesus
イエスに大胆に
粘り強くお願いしました
for her demon-possessed daughter.
願い通り癒やされました
And she got that help, didn’t she?
マルタは兄弟を亡くして
悲しみに暮れていましたが
Martha, after the painful loss
of her brother to the enemy death,
イエスが死者を復活させることが
できると信じていました
maintained faith in Jesus’ ability
to raise the dead.
最後の話では 現代の
2人の例に注目しました
The two modern-day examples
that we discussed in the last talk,
石井姉妹とトーム姉妹です
Sisters Ishii and Toom,
both steadfastly refused to compromise
2人とも エホバの証人だという理由で
何年も拘禁されました
despite being imprisoned for many years
それでも 信仰を捨てることを
きっぱり拒みました
simply because they were
Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Yes, each one of these dear sisters faced
石井姉妹もトーム姉妹も
山のような問題にぶつかりました
mountainlike obstacles
but Jehovah rewarded their faith.
でもエホバは2人の信仰に報いました
2人はエホバが良いことを
してくれると信じていました
Their faith moved them
to expect good things from Jehovah,
そして実際にエホバから祝福されました
and Jehovah never ever let them down.
Well, what good things
do we expect from Jehovah
強い信仰を保つなら
エホバがどんなことをしてくれると
期待できますか
if we maintain strong faith?
Let’s talk about some of the events
間もなく起きると予告されている事柄を
幾つか考えてみましょう
that we expect to unfold in the near future.
Now, for one thing, the final part
of Nebuchadnezzar’s image dream
例えば ダニエル 2章に出てくる
ネブカドネザルの像の夢の
最後の部分が実現します
discussed in Daniel chapter 2
will be fulfilled.
As represented by the four upper parts
of that image,
像の上から4つの部分で表される
four world powers have come and gone,
4つの強国は すでに現れ
過ぎ去りました
just as prophesied.
予告通りにです
Today, the Anglo-American World Power,
今 世界に大きな影響を与えているのは
symbolized by the feet of iron and clay,
鉄と粘土でできた足で
表されている英米です
is dominating.
And more than ever,
we see this last world power
私たちは この最後の強国が
living up to being a noncohesive mixture
鉄と粘土のように分裂した様子を
これまで以上に見ています
of iron and clay.
And just as iron mixed with clay
粘土が混ざった鉄が
鉄の塊より弱いのと同じように
is weaker than solid iron,
英米は鉄のような
ローマ帝国より弱いと言えます
so too the Anglo-American World Power
is weaker
than the ironlike Roman Empire
from which it emerged.
ローマ帝国は 英米の
母体となった帝国です
英米は 粘土のようなものによって
The ability of the Anglo-American World Power
to act with ironlike strength
鉄のような強さを
発揮することができません
is weakened by claylike elements,
例えば 暴動によって権利を
主張する人たちがいます
such as people rising up
to claim their rights
公民権運動や独立運動を
行う人たちもいます
through insurrection,
civil rights campaigns,
このような人たちが足の粘土の部分です
and independence movements.
As Daniel foretold in chapter 2, verse 42:
ダニエル 2:42にはこうあります
「この王国には強い部分と
もろい部分があることになります」
“The kingdom will be partly strong
and partly fragile.”
今そのことは かつてないほど
明らかになっています
And we see that is
more and more evident today than ever.
この最後の強国は弱体化しているものの
But despite the weakened condition
of this final world power,
そのまま力を失って
it will not simply disintegrate
into self-destruction.
自滅するわけではありません
Go to Daniel chapter 2,
and let’s notice how it comes to its end.
ダニエル 2章を開いて
どうなるか見てみましょう
It’s a very familiar scripture here
—Daniel 2:44:
ダニエル 2:44からです
「この王たちの時代に
“In the days of those kings the God of heaven
天の神は決して滅ぼされることのない
王国を建てます
“will set up a kingdom
that will never be destroyed.
その王国はほかのどんな民にも
渡されません
“And this kingdom will not be passed on
to any other people.
“It will crush and put an end
to all these kingdoms,
これらの王国を全て打ち砕いて終わらせ
その王国だけが永遠に存続します
“and it alone will stand forever,
“just as you saw that out of the mountain
a stone was cut not by hands
山から1つの石が人手によらずに
［つまりエホバの手によって］
切り出され
“[that is, not by human hands,
but by Jehovah’s hands],
鉄 銅 粘土 銀 金を打ち砕いたのを
“and that it crushed the iron, the copper,
“the clay, the silver, and the gold.
あなたがご覧になった通りです
“The Grand God has made known to the king
what will happen in the future.
偉大な神が 将来起きる事柄を
王に知らせました
“The dream is true,
この夢は真実であり
and its interpretation is trustworthy.”
解き明かしも確かです」
This scripture describes how God’s Kingdom,
石で表される神の王国は
ハルマゲドンで人間の政府を
打ち砕きます
represented by that stone,
will crush all human governments
全ての政府を滅ぼすのです
at Armageddon.
興味深いことに
ダニエル 2:34によると
And interestingly, at Daniel 2:34,
it tells us that ‘the stone [God’s Kingdom]
「石［つまり神の王国］が
‘will strike the image
[representing human governments]
［人間の政府を表す］像の
鉄と粘土でできた足の所を打」ちます
in the feet of iron and clay,’
clearly identifying that Armageddon will come
何が分かりますか
ハルマゲドンは 人間が支配する
最後の強国である
during the time
of the Anglo-American World Power
英米がまだ存続している間に
来る ということです
—the final human world power.
And like Daniel, we have strong faith
私たちはダニエルと同じように
次のことを確信しています
in the last sentence of verse 45, which says:
45節の最後です
“The dream is true, and its interpretation
「この夢は真実であり
解き明かしも確かです」
is trustworthy.”
疑問の余地はありません
There’s no doubt about it:
God’s Kingdom will destroy
神の王国は英米が存続している間に
all human governments at Armageddon
ハルマゲドンで人間の全ての
政府を滅ぼすのです
during the time
of the Anglo-American World Power.
But now, just as the final part
of the image dream
像の夢の最後の部分が
間もなく実現するのと同じように
will soon be fulfilled,
the final part of Daniel’s vision
in chapter 7
ダニエル 7章の幻の最後の部分も
間もなく実現します
will soon be fulfilled.
Now, in chapter 7,
Daniel describes four wild beasts,
ダニエルが見たこの幻には
獣が4匹出てきます
which symbolize four world powers
that have come and gone.
これらの獣はかつて存在した
4つの強国を表しています
And appropriately,
they’re described as wild beasts
この獣という表現はぴったりです
支配の仕方が穏やかでなく
because they haven’t ruled kindly
but, rather, in a harsh, beastly way.
獣のように荒々しいからです
Now, those four world powers
この4つの強国とは
バビロン メディア･ペルシャ
ギリシャ ローマです
are Babylon, Medo-Persia, Greece, and Rome
—the very same four world powers
ここに出てくる4つの国は
represented by the four upper metal parts
像の上から4つの部分が
表す国と同じです
of the image dream we discussed previously.
先ほど考えたダニエル 2章の像です
ダニエルは7:8で
But in verse 8, Daniel describes a horn
ローマを表す4匹目の獣の頭から
生えてきた角に注意を向けています
that grew out of the head
of that fourth beast—out of Rome;
その角には目があり
that horn had eyes; that horn had a mouth;
口があり 高慢に語ります
that mouth spoke arrogantly.
Well, this arrogant horn symbolizes
この高慢な角は何を表していますか
英米を表しています
the Anglo-American World Power
繰り返しますが 最後の強国です
—again, the last world power.
Now, what was foretold to happen next?
次にどうなることが予告されていますか
ダニエル 7章を見てみましょう
We’ll go to Daniel chapter 7, please.
次に起きる事柄です
Let’s see what happens next.
Daniel chapter 7,
ダニエル 7:26から
読んでみましょう
and please let’s begin in verse number 26:
「しかし 法廷が開廷し
“But the Court sat,
彼の統治権［つまり高慢な角の
統治権］を取り去りました
“and they took away his rulership
[that is, that horn’s rulership],
“in order to annihilate him
and to destroy him completely.
彼を根絶やしにし
完全に滅ぼすためです
王国と 統治権と 天の下の
全ての王国の栄光は
“And the kingdom and the rulership
and the grandeur
“of the kingdoms under all the heavens
至上者の聖なる者たちに与えられました
“were given to the people
“who are the holy ones of the Supreme One.
彼らの王国は永遠に存続し
“Their kingdom is an everlasting kingdom,
全ての国の人々は
彼らに仕え 従います」
and all rulerships will serve and obey them.”
この高慢な角は統治権を取り去られ
The rulership of this arrogant horn
is taken away,
根絶やしにされ 滅ぼされ
and it is annihilated and destroyed
代わりに神の王国が統治します
and replaced by God’s Kingdom.
So just as described
in the imagery in this vision,
この幻で描写されている通り
神の王国は最後の強国である
英米が存続している間に
we see that God’s Kingdom
destroys all human governments
人間の全ての政府を滅ぼします
during the time
of the Anglo-American World Power
そして地球全体を治めるようになります
and then takes over rulership of the earth.
How exciting that event,
胸の躍るような出来事です
こうしたことが間もなく生じるのです
which will take place
in the near future, will be!
考えてみてください この預言は
今まで全て実現してきました
But think about it: Every preceding part
of that prophecy has come true.
So we have complete confidence, strong faith,
ですから この預言の最後の部分も
必ず実現すると
100パーセント確信できます
that the final part of it
will also come true.
Now, there are many other prophecies
in the book of Daniel
今日は取り上げる時間が
ありませんでしたが
ダニエル書にはほかにも
たくさんの預言があり
that we didn’t have time to discuss
that have come true in amazing detail.
詳細な点に至るまで実現してきました
これほど多くの預言が
実現しているということは
But the fulfillment of so many prophecies
totally convinces us
この体制の終わりが
that we are deep, deep
in “the time of the end.”
非常に 非常に近い証拠です
Very soon, we’re going to witness
間もなく私たちはダニエル 12:1の
預言の実現を目撃することでしょう
the fulfillment of Daniel 12:1,
which talks about ‘Michael the great prince
その預言によると 「偉大な長
ミカエルが行動を起こします」
standing up.’
“And there will occur
a time of [great] distress.”
「そして［大きな］苦難の時が来ます」
しかし 神の民は「逃れます」
But God’s “people will escape,
「書に記されている人は
皆 逃れ」るのです
everyone who is found
written down in the book.”
In the video near the beginning of this talk,
この話の最初の方で見たビデオでは
we saw Michael, the glorified Jesus Christ,
ミカエルつまり栄光を受けた
イエス･キリストが
depicted as coming with the angels
天使と共に来て 神の民を救出し
to rescue Jehovah’s people
今の邪悪な体制を滅ぼす様子が
描かれていました
and destroy this wicked system.
But now, if you notice carefully
in that video,
ビデオをよく見ると分かりますが
敵たちは銃を空に向けて
the wicked were actually shooting
their weapons
ミカエルを撃とうとしていました
into the sky at Michael.
Now, that’s laughable
—isn’t it?—
無駄な抵抗です
人間が造った最も強力な武器も
because mankind’s most powerful weapons
are like wet firecrackers
ミカエルの力に比べれば
compared to Michael’s mighty power.
しけた花火のようなものです
ビデオに出てきたミカエルは
In fact, in the video,
Michael was depicted as coming
防御用の装備を
身に着けていませんでした
with no defensive equipment,
such as a breastplate or shield.
胸当ても盾もありませんでした
必要ないのです
He doesn’t need it.
He was depicted only with a sword
持っていたのは剣だけです
—an offensive weapon.
攻撃用の武器です
Now, sometimes in our illustrations,
he’s depicted with a bow and arrow
挿絵によってはイエスが
弓と矢を持っています
—again, only an offensive weapon.
やはり攻撃用の武器しか持っていません
But his offensive weapons are powerful
でもイエスが攻撃に使う武器は強力です
その武器にはすさまじい威力があります
—much, much more powerful
than needed to do the job
of rescuing Jehovah’s people
ですから エホバの民を救出し
サタンの邪悪な体制全体を
一掃するのは簡単なことです
and sweeping out of existence
Satan’s entire wicked system.
But then after Armageddon,
ハルマゲドンの後 キリスト･イエスの
輝かしい千年統治が始まります
the glorious Thousand Year Reign
of Christ Jesus will begin.
その素晴らしい時の間
And during that marvelous time,
the last verse
ダニエル書の最後の節が実現します
of the book of Daniel will be fulfilled.
読んでみましょう
ダニエル書の最後の節 12:13です
Now let’s read it.
The last verse of this book, chapter 12,
and let’s read verse 13.
ダニエルに語られた言葉です
And here’s what was said to Daniel:
“But as for you, go on to the end.
「あなたは最後まで進んでいきなさい
あなたは休みますが
“You will rest, but you will stand up
日々の終わりに 報いを
受けるために立ち上がります」
for your lot at the end of the days.”
Yes, Daniel served Jehovah faithfully
ダニエルは生涯の最後まで
エホバに忠実に仕えました
until the end of his life.
「最後まで進ん［だ］」のです
He went “to the end,” didn’t he?
Now he’s resting in death,
今は死んで休んでいますが
間もなく復活して「立ち上がります」
but soon he “will stand up”
in the resurrection
キリストの千年統治の間
「報い」を受けます
during Christ’s Millennial Reign
“for [his] lot”—his place in the new world.
新しい世界での報いです
エホバが天使を通して約束したことに
But we ask, Did Daniel have faith
in that promise
ダニエルは信仰を持ちましたか
that Jehovah gave him through the angel?
For a certainty, he did!
もちろん 持ちました
すでに何十年も信仰を示していました
He had already demonstrated
faith for decades.
美食を勧められても食べませんでした
He remained clean when tempted to eat food
自分を汚したくなかったからです
that would defile him.
He was diligent in prayer,
毎日欠かさず祈りました
even when praying meant
that he would be executed.
処刑されると脅されてもそうしました
He never stopped building his faith
through Bible study.
聖書をよく学び 信仰を強め続けました
So we can be sure
he believed with all his heart
ですから ダニエルはエホバが
天使を通して約束したことを
that promise Jehovah gave him
through the angel
心から信じたに違いありません
復活して立ち上がり 新しい世界で
報いを受けるという約束です
—that he would stand up in the resurrection
and take his place in the new world.
では どうでしょうか
But now we ask,
How can we maintain our faith
私たちはどうすれば
ダニエルのように信仰を保てますか
as Daniel did?
信仰を弱めないようにするため
Well, by staying morally
and spiritually clean,
エホバとの絆を大切にし
道徳的な清さを保ちましょう
not allowing anything to corrupt our faith;
by praying constantly
いつも祈ってください
エホバが必ず聞いてくれる
という確信を抱きましょう
with full confidence that Jehovah
will answer our prayers;
聖書をよく学ぶことによって
and by listening to Jehovah
by diligent study of his Word.
エホバの言葉を注意深く聞いてください
エホバは私たちに
報いたいと願っています
Jehovah wants us to have faith
そのことを信じてほしいと思っています
that he is our Rewarder.
ヘブライ 11:6にはこうあります
Hebrews 11:6 says:
“Whoever approaches God must believe
that he is [that he’s really there]
「神に近づく人は
神が存在し［本当にいて］
熱心に仕えようと努める人たちに
“and that he becomes the rewarder
報いてくださる ということを
信じなければなりません」
of those earnestly seeking him.”
ビデオに出てきた2人の
兄弟のことを思い出してください
Think about our two brothers
shown earlier in this talk:
クリスチャンである父親と
病気の兄弟です
the Christian father and the sick brother.
父親は結局逮捕されました
The Christian father ended up behind bars,
and our sick brother
was not miraculously healed.
病気の兄弟は
回復したわけではありません
では2人の信仰は無駄でしたか
So was their faith in vain?
そのようなことは決してありません
For a certainty, no!
エホバは2人に報いますか
Will Jehovah reward them?
For a certainty, yes!
もちろん 報います
あなたが同じような
状況に置かれているなら
If you are facing a similar situation,
エホバはあなたに報いますか
will Jehovah reward you?
Most definitely yes!
もちろん 報います
Please watch the following video
次のビデオをご覧ください
which features the song that we will sing
大会の最後にみんなで歌う
オリジナルソングの
ミュージックビデオです
to conclude our convention.
どうぞお楽しみください
Enjoy this video.
炎のように迫る敵たち
Why should I fear the lion?
Why should I fear any foe?
恐れはしない
With Jehovah by my side,
いつもそばにエホバがいるから
I will not run and hide.
My God is with me; this I know.
あなたの助けを信じ
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
あなたから離れない
With eyes of faith,
there’s nothing more to fear.
力もらって強くなろう
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
進みつづけていこう
Knowing that my God is always near—
あなたと
With eyes of faith.
エホバは友を忘れることなく
Those faithful ones before us
Lived their lives in loyalty.
また再び目覚めさせる 新しい世界で
By their faith they endured.
Their future is assured.
They’ll stand again for all to see.
あなたの助けを信じ
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
あなたから離れない
With eyes of faith,
there’s nothing more to fear.
力もらって強くなろう
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
進みつづけていこう
Knowing that my God is always near—
あなたと
With eyes of faith.
確かな希望がある
With eyes of faith, I can move a mountain.
試練の向こうに
With eyes of faith, my hope is sure.
揺るがず立ちつづけていく
Where would I be
Without the faith that helps me see
信仰抱いて
Beyond the trials I endure?
未来が見える もう目の前に
I see the wondrous future
God has in store for me.
守り抜く この信仰
I need to be strong.
I know it won’t be long
エホバの勝利まで
Till Jehovah claims his victory.
あなたの助けを信じ
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
あなたから離れない
With eyes of faith,
there’s nothing more to fear.
力もらって強くなろう
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
進みつづけていこう
Knowing that my God is always near—
未来へ
With eyes of faith,
エホバと
With eyes of faith.
本当に心を揺さぶられるビデオでした
What a powerfully motivating video!
And we look forward to singing that song
大会の最後に 皆さんと一緒に
この歌を歌えるのがとても楽しみです
to conclude our convention.
Dear brothers and sisters,
愛する兄弟姉妹 子供たち
faithful children,
聖書に関心を持つ皆さん
cherished interested ones,
私たちは今強力な敵と戦っています
there’s no doubt that right now
we face powerful enemies.
For one thing, we have a powerful enemy
1つは私たち自身の
中にいる強力な敵です
inside our bodies
—inherited sin.
受け継いだ罪です
It wages an intense war
against our desire to do what is right.
この敵は 正しいことをしたいという
私たちの願いを攻撃します
Secondly, we have the formidable foes:
2つ目に 非常に強力な敵である
サタンと邪悪な天使たちがいます
Satan and his demons.
サタンは聖書で むさぼり食うライオン
Satan is described as a devouring lion,
a cunning serpent,
こうかつな蛇 どう猛な竜
a fierce dragon,
鳥をわなで捕る者などと呼ばれる
危険な存在です
a sneaky birdcatcher,
and he’s given other evil descriptions.
エフェソス 6:12にある通り
「私たちは戦っている
Ephesians 6:12 says:
“We have a struggle
[the footnote, literally “a wrestling”]
［直訳によると 格闘をして］
いるからです⋯⋯
. . . against the wicked spirit forces
in the heavenly places.”
天にいる邪悪な天使の
勢力と戦っています」
出版物の中で説明されている通り
And as mentioned in our publications,
there may be tens of thousands
邪悪で強力な天使が
of these powerful, evil spirit creatures
目に見えない領域に非常に大勢いて
in the invisible realm
waging war against us.
私たちに戦いを仕掛けています
3つ目は 周囲の邪悪な世界です
Thirdly, we have this wicked world
all around us
that is trying to assimilate us
私たちに圧力をかけて
神に喜ばれないことをさせようとします
into joining them in ungodly conduct.
And looking at the ratio,
人口比で見ると
we as Jehovah’s people
are outnumbered by people of the world
エホバの民の数は そうではない
人たちと比べて非常に少数です
by about 900 to 1.
約900人に1人です
But despite the power
of those three great enemies,
この3つの敵は非常に強力ですが
宇宙で最も強力な力である
聖なる力が生み出す信仰があれば
our faith—this product
of Jehovah’s invincible holy spirit—
makes us stronger and stronger individually
私たち一人一人はますます強くなり
この3つの敵全てに
立ち向かうことができます
than all of those three enemies combined.
間もなく もう1つの強力な敵が
私たちを攻撃します
In the near future,
another powerful enemy will come against us.
This formidable foe
この恐ろしい敵は
エゼキエル 38章でゴグと
呼ばれている諸国家の連合体です
is a coalition of nations
called Gog in Ezekiel chapter 38.
And Ezekiel chapter 38 says
that Gog will come with “a great assembly,
エゼキエル 38章によると
ゴグは「大勢いて
大軍を成して」います
a vast army.”
“Like clouds covering the land,”
「土地を覆う雲のように」
神の民に攻撃を仕掛けます
they will come against God’s people.
非常に恐ろしい状況になることでしょう
Now, this could be
a very intimidating situation.
でも愛する兄弟姉妹 信仰があれば
But dear brothers and sisters,
your faith will make you stronger than Gog
ゴグより強くなることができます
皆さんはますます強くなります
and will keep you strong
そしてエホバはハルマゲドンで
奇跡的に救出してくれます
until Jehovah miraculously intervenes
at Armageddon.
And if you think about it,
Armageddon really is a rescue operation.
ハルマゲドンは救出作戦です
エホバは行動を起こし
He will intervene,
神の民を攻撃するゴグを
「滅亡のほうき」で一掃します
and he will sweep attacking Gog away forever
with a “broom of annihilation.”
ゴグは完全にいなくなります
昔 神の民は信仰によって
In the past, faith has helped God’s people
非常に大きな問題を
乗り越えることができました
to overcome the most powerful obstacles,
and that same product of holy spirit
私たちも信仰があれば
問題を乗り越えられます
will help us do the same.
Yes, throughout the centuries,
just like today,
今も昔も同じです
ダニエルなど神に仕えた人たちが
God’s servants, such as Daniel,
have been made powerful,
強くなれたのは
自分に力があったからではなく
信仰があったからです
not by natural strength, but through faith.
では愛する兄弟姉妹
So dear brothers and sisters,
faithful children,
子供たち
聖書に関心を持つ皆さん
cherished interested ones,
信仰を祈り求めてください
pray earnestly for faith.
信仰のために真剣に戦いましょう
Put up a hard fight to maintain your faith.
次のことを固く信じてください
And trust with all your heart
that if you have faith,
信仰があれば 信仰を保てば
信仰によって歩めば
maintain your faith, and walk by faith,
you definitely will see
あなたは必ず
エホバの約束が全て実現するのを
見ることができるでしょう
all of Jehovah’s promises fulfilled.
Thank you, Brother Lett.
ありがとうございました
レット兄弟の話と この地区大会
全体によって信仰が強められ
Your talk and this entire convention
have strengthened our faith
and prepared us for future events.
将来に備えることができました
All in attendance will be pleased to know
皆さんにうれしいお知らせがあります
that Parts I and II of the drama
「ダニエル 信仰を貫いた人」という
ドラマの第1部と第2部を
Daniel: A Lifetime of Faith
are available now for download on jw.org
jw.orgと
JW Library®アプリで
and in the JW Library® {
ダウンロードすることができます
This convention is further proof that Jehovah
この大会を通して
世界の状況が厳しい中でも
and his Son, Jesus Christ,
私たちが強い信仰を
保つために必要なものを
provide abundantly for our spiritual needs
エホバとイエスが豊かに与えて
くださることを確信できました
despite difficult world conditions.
How we rejoice to be in their loving care!
本当に感謝できるのではないでしょうか
And on behalf of the Governing Body
ここで 統治体の兄弟たちと
and all the hardworking members
of our Bethel families
世界中で熱心に働いているベテル家族や
翻訳事務所の兄弟姉妹を代表して
and translation offices around the world,
we thank you for watching
2021地区大会を視聴して
くださったことに感謝いたします
the 2021 regional convention program.
We love you.
私たちは皆さんを愛しており
May your love and faith remain strong,
皆さんが愛や信仰や希望を
強く保つことを願っています
and may your hope remain bright.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
JW Broadcasting®が
お送りしてきました
this is JW Broadcasting®.
Let’s conclude now by singing a song
最後に 信仰を持って歩み続ける
決意を表す歌を歌いましょう
that expresses the power
that faith has in our lives.
Please join in singing the original song
「信仰を抱いて」と題する
オリジナルソングを歌いたいと思います
“With Eyes of Faith,”
which we heard sung
during the concluding talk.
結びの話の中で聞いた歌です
After the song,
歌の後 それぞれの場所で
結びの祈りを捧げてください
you may have your concluding prayer
at your individual locations.
Now we invite all to sing out
では ものみの塔コーラス隊と
一緒に大きな声で歌いましょう
along with the Watchtower chorus
“With Eyes of Faith.”
「信仰を抱いて」